Guide to the President's Office Records of William Jasper Kerr 1907-1964
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
President's Office Records of William Jasper Kerr
1907-1964
1907-1940
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & University Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu
RG 013 - SG 07
Oregon State Agricultural College. Office of the President.
1.75 cubic feet 5 boxes, including 1 oversize box
5 microfilm reels
The President's Office Records of William Jasper Kerr document Kerr's presidency of Oregon Agricultural College between 1907 and 1932 and include materials from his tenure as Chancellor of Oregon's higher education system. The collection includes general reference files, correspondence, newsclippings, assorted reports and publications, and materials generated for the Oregon State Board of Higher Education and the Board of Regents. The collection contains materials relating to the college's educational mission, organizational structure, budget, attendance, and curricular offerings, the state of education in Oregon, and the reorganization of the Oregon educational system.
Historical Note:
William Jasper Kerr was born November 17, 1863 in Richmond, Utah. At a young age, Kerr dropped out of school in favor of a position on his father's railroad construction crew. He later returned to school, earning a B.S. in mathematics from the University of Utah in 1885. Following graduation, Kerr accepted a position teaching in Smithfield, Utah. Shortly thereafter, he was promoted to Superintendent of the Smithfield district. Between 1887 and 1894, Kerr taught mathematics at Brigham Young College and the University of Utah. In 1894, Kerr was appointed President of Brigham Young, a position he held until 1900 when he became President of Utah State Agricultural College. In 1907, Kerr resigned his position at Utah and became President of Oregon Agricultural College.
Kerr's presidency at OAC was defined by a period of prolonged and aggressive growth. During his tenure, the college constructed more than twenty buildings, including the Memorial Union, and more than doubled the total size of the campus to 555 acres. He tightened admissions requirements, expanded curricular offerings, and added talented staff to the college's ranks. Kerr resigned from his post in 1932, ending the longest reign of any OSC president.
After leaving the college, Kerr became the first Chancellor of Oregon's system of higher education. He held this position for three years before retiring. William Jasper Kerr died in 1947 at the age of 83.
The President's Office Records of William Jasper Kerr are comprised of materials from Kerr's tenure as President of Oregon Agricultural College. The collection include a general reference file, correspondence, newspaper clippings, communications with the Oregon State Board of Higher Education, publications, reports to the Board of Regents, survey materials, and biographic materials. The collection contains extensive material relating to the physical and curricular growth of the college, the controversial reorganization of OAC and the University of Oregon, and the state of higher education in Oregon in the early 20th century.
The President's Office records of William Jasper Kerr are arranged into eleven series: I: General Reference File, 1922-1940; II: Correspondence, 1907-1935; III: Clippings, 1908-1935; IV: Oregon State Board of Higher Curricula, 1925-1941; V: Resolutions Adopted by the State Board of Higher Education, 1935; VI: Biography of William Jasper Kerr; VII: Publications, 1908-1964; VIII: The OSC - U of O Controversy, 1937; IX: Reports to the Board of Regents, 1909-1929; X: Reorganization, 1931-1932; XI: College Surveys, 1928-1930. Materials within series are arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
The collection is open for research.
These records were transferred to the University Archives by the OSU President's Office. The collection is now held by the Oregon State University Libraries Special Collections & Archives Research Center.
Related Materials
Content related to the Kerr presidency can be found in the Edwin T. Reed Papers and Subgroup 12 of the President's Office Records. Additional materials relating to the presidents of Oregon State University include the President's Office Records (RG 013), the Presidents of Oregon State University Photographic Collection (P 001), the President's Office Photographs Collection (P 092), the President's Office Motion Picture Film and Videotapes Collection (FV P 092), the Board of Regents Records (RG 008), the Board of Trustees Records (RG 033), and the the Oregon State University Memorabilia Collection.
Kerr, William Jasper, 1863-1947.; Reed, Edwin Thomas, 1872-1948.
Oregon State Agricultural College. Board of Regents.; Oregon State College. Office of the President.; United States. Bureau of Education.; Association of American Universities.; Oregon Agricultural College.; Oregon State Agricultural College.; Oregon State Board of Higher Curricula.; Oregon State System of Higher Education.; University of Oregon.
Universities and colleges--Curricula--Oregon--Corvallis.; College presidents--Oregon--Corvallis.; Universities and colleges--Law and legislation--Oregon.; Education, Higher--Oregon.
Advertising and Marketing; Agriculture; Colleges and Universities; Corvallis; Oregon
- General Reference File, 1922-1940; Series I
  Series I contains reports, correspondence, notes, and clippings related to agriculture in Oregon. The material spans the latter portion of Kerr's career at Oregon Agricultural College and his time as the state's Chancellor of higher education. Subjects referenced in this series include agricultural and industrial production, marketing and sales, construction, public works, agricultural sciences, college and government employees, trade law, and government organizations.
  - Oregon Production Statistics, 1933-1937 (Reel-folder 80.1)
  - Production in Oregon and Washington, 1934-1936 (Reel-folder 80.2)
  - Oregon Private Marketing Firms, 1937 (Reel-folder 80.3)
  - Marketing Agreements - Oregon, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 80.4)
  - Cauliflower Marketing Agreements - Oregon, 1937 (Reel-folder 80.5)
  - Hops Stabilization Program, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 80.6)
  - Walnut Control Board, 1936 (Reel-folder 80.7)
  - Marketing Cooperative, 1932-1938 (Reel-folder 80.8)
  - Oregon Agricultural and Industrial Marketing Study, 1938 (Reel-folder 80.9)
  - Marketing Organizations in Oregon and Washington, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 80.10)
  - Cooperative Organizations - Summary Agriculture and Lumber, 1935-1938 (Reel-folder 80.11)
  - Hood River Apple Growers Association, 1934-1937 (Reel-folder 80.12)
  - Interstate Associated Creameries, 1934-1938 (Reel-folder 80.13)
  - Northwest Dried Food Association, 1937 (Reel-folder 80.14)
  - Oregon Growers Union, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 80.15)
  - Oregon Prune Control Board Incorporated, 1936 (Reel-folder 80.16)
  - Oregon-Washington Pear Bureau, 1936 (Reel-folder 80.17)
  - Oregon-Washington-California Pear League Inc., 1937 (Reel-folder 80.18)
  - Pacific Cooperative Poultry Producers, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 80.19)
  - Pacific Wool Growers, Portland, Oregon, 1937 (Reel-folder 80.20)
  - Southern Oregon Sales Inc., Medford, Oregon, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 80.21)
  - Tillamook County Creamery Association, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 80.22)
  - "Oregon's Problem in Maketing Agricultural & Industrial Products", 1938 (Reel-folder 80.23)
  - Research Production and Marketing - Reports, Correspondence, Memoranda and other material, 1936-1939 (Reel-folder 80.24)
  - Report of Agricultural Investigating Committee - Governor Martin, 1937-1939 (Reel-folder 80.25)
  - Oregon Marketing, 1939-1940 (Reel-folder 80.26)
  - Agricultural and Industrial Marketing, 1937-1939 (Reel-folder 81.27)
  - Marketing Miscellaneous, 1937-1940 (Reel-folder 81.28)
  - Services of Oregon State Agricultural College in Marketing Oregon Products, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.29)
  - Marketing Report Miscellaneous Editorials, 1935, 1938 (Reel-folder 81.30)
  - Marketing Report Miscellaneous News Stories, 1935-1939 (Reel-folder 81.31)
  - Marketing - Chancellor Hunter, 1938 (Reel-folder 81.32)
  - Marketing Report Oregon Journal Editorials, 1935-1939 (Reel-folder 81.33)
  - Marketing Report Oregon Journal News Stories, 1935-1939 (Reel-folder 81.34)
  - Marketing Report The Oregonian Editorials, 1935-1939 (Reel-folder 81.35)
  - Marketing Report The Oregonian News Stories, 1937-1939 (Reel-folder 81.36)
  - "What the State Does in Educational Preparatin for Marketing", 1939 (Reel-folder 81.37)
  - Division of Marketing State Board of Higher Education, 1938 (Reel-folder 81.38)
  - By-products - Culls, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 81.39)
  - Cooperative Organization Problems, 1930-1937 (Reel-folder 81.40)
  - Farm Purchasing Associations, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 81.41)
  - Food Preparation, 1935-1936 (Reel-folder 81.42)
  - Brand Names, undated (Reel-folder 81.43)
  - Flax Seed and Flax Fiber Possibilities, 1936-1940 (Reel-folder 81.44)
  - Industrial Uses for Farm Products, 1934-1938 (Reel-folder 81.45)
  - Industrial Uses for Farm Products - Power Motor Alcohol, 1934-1937 (Reel-folder 81.46)
  - Irrigation, 1934-1938 (Reel-folder 81.47)
  - "Possibilities for Livestock Fattening in Oregon", 1936 (Reel-folder 81.48)
  - Merchandising, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 81.49)
  - Milk Distribution Problems, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 81.50)
  - Other Domestic Market Outlets, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 81.51)
  - Packaging, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 81.52)
  - Processing, 1934-1938 (Reel-folder 81.53)
  - Producer - Consumer Sales Campaigns, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.54)
  - Prune Industry in Oregon - Governor Sprague, 1939-1940 (Reel-folder 81.55)
  - Special Prune Committee - Glenn Hogg, Chairman, 1939-1940 (Reel-folder 81.56)
  - Marketing Conference State System of Higher Education - Governor Sprague, 1939-1940 (Reel-folder 81.57)
  - Marketing Oregon Prunes, 1931, 1938-1940 (Reel-folder 81.58)
  - Grading of Agricultural Products, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 81.59)
  - Sugar Beet Industry, 1936-1940 (Reel-folder 81.60)
  - Transportation, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 81.61)
  - Unfair Trade Practices, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 81.62)
  - Agricultural Engineering Foundation - San Francisco, California, Oswold Wilson, Mngr., 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 81.63)
  - Ashland Chamber of Commerce, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.64)
  - Bonneville Dam Project, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 81.65)
  - Cooperative Grange League Federation Exchange, Inc. Ithaca, New York, 1936 (Reel-folder 81.66)
  - Dairy Cooperative Association, Portland, Oregon, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 81.67)
  - Eugene Fruit Growers Exchange, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 81.68)
  - Farm Security Administration (Resettlement Administration), 1937 (Reel-folder 81.69)
  - Federal Farm Board, 1930 (Reel-folder 81.70)
  - Fruit Growers League, Medford, Oregon, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.71)
  - Winter Pears--Henry Hartman, 1935-136 (Reel-folder 81.72)
  - Idaho Department of State, Boise, Idaho, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.73)
  - National Emergency Council, 1936 (Reel-folder 81.74)
  - National Farm Chemurgic Council, Dearborn, Michigan, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.75)
  - National Youth Administration, 1935-1936 (Reel-folder 81.76)
  - Oregon State Planning Board, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 81.77)
  - Pacific Northwest Advisory Board, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 81.78)
  - Pacific Northwest Regional Planning Commission, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 81.79)
  - Portland Chamber of Commerce - Lumber Products, 1935 (Reel-folder 81.80)
  - Social Science Research Council, undated (Reel-folder 81.81)
  - U.S. Forest Service, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 81.82)
  - Population Developments, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.83)
  - General Correspondence, 1933-1938 (Reel-folder 81.84)
  - J.R. Beck, 1936 (Reel-folder 81.85)
  - H.K. Benson, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.86)
  - "Preliminary Study for Proposed Bonneville Industries", undated (Reel-folder 81.87)
  - A.G.B. Bouquet, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.88)
  - W.D. Bristol, 1937 (Reel-folder 81.89)
  - L.R. Breithaupt, Extension Agricultural Economist, 1935-1938 (Reel-folder 81.90)
  - Gordon G. Brown, Hood River Experiment Station, 1935 (Reel-folder 81.91)
  - W.S. Brown, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 81.92)
  - Paul Carpenter, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 81.93)
  - Paul Carpenter (continued), 1936 (Reel-folder 82.93)
  - R.L. Clark, Bodine and Clark Commission Company, 1936 (Reel-folder 82.94)
  - Berkeley Davis, 1937 (Reel-folder 82.95)
  - William Einzig, Great Western Malting Company Inc., 1938 (Reel-folder 82.96)
  - A.E. Engbretson, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 82.97)
  - Eric Englund, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 82.98)
  - A.C. Forrester, Industrial Distilleries, 1935-1937 (Reel-folder 82.99)
  - Dan D. Freeman, Oregon Manufacturer's Association, 1936 (Reel-folder 82.100)
  - O.G. Hughson, 1935-1936 (Reel-folder 82.101)
  - G.R. Hyslop, 1936-1938 (Reel-folder 82.102)
  - E.R. Jackman, Oregon State College, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 82.103)
  - Arthur S. King, 1937 (Reel-folder 82.104)
  - George M. Knox, Hood River County Assessor, 1937 (Reel-folder 82.105)
  - L.L. Laws, 1940 (Reel-folder 82.106)
  - Earl G. Mason, 1937 (Reel-folder 82.107)
  - Victor P. Morris, 1937 (Reel-folder 82.108)
  - Harry L. Riches, Marion County Agent, 1936 (Reel-folder 82.109)
  - J. L. Taylor, Vale Chamber of Commerce, 1937-1938 (Reel-folder 82.110)
  - I. H. Vanwinkle, Attorney General, 1938 (Reel-folder 82.111)
  - E.H. Wiegand, 1936-1937 (Reel-folder 82.112)
  - Walter C. Winslow, 1938 (Reel-folder 82.113)
  - American Association of University Women, 1922-1927 (Reel 180)
  - Emergency Board Request for Extension Service & Experiment Station, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Statement of Services Lost to the Institution & State for the Year 1931-32, December 1931 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1907-1935; Series II
  Series II includes correspondence relating to the management and operation of Oregon Agricultural College. The series contains correspondence between William Jasper Kerr, OAC faculty, the Association of American Universities, students, figures associated with the institution, and the general public. Topics include equipment and materials for college use, reports from faculty members, the donation of a McCormick Reaper replica, legislation impacting OAC, Extension Service programming, faculty appointments, and budget matters.
  - Microfilmed Correspondence, 1907-1929 (Reel 82)
  - Original Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Original Correspondence, 1930-1935 (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1908-1935; Series III
  Series III is comprised of newspaper clippings relating to Oregon Agricultural College. Subjects include state educational funding, college attendance, faculty activities and research, development of the campus, and OAC's curricular offerings. The series contains both photocopies and a selection of original clippings.
  - General, 1908-1909 (Box 1)
  - General, 1910 (Box 1)
  - General, 1911 (Box 1)
  - General, 1912 (Box 1)
  - General, 1913 (Box 1)
  - General, 1932 (Box 1)
  - General, 1935 (Box 1)
  - General, undated (Box 1)
  - Selected originals of newspaper clippings, 1909-1932 (Box 5)
- Oregon State Board of Higher Curricula, 1925-1941; Series IV
  Series IV contains official reports and statements made by Oregon Agricultural College to the Oregon State Board of Higher Curricula between 1925 and 1941. The series also contains an outline of a plan for dividing programmatic efforts between the University of Oregon and OAC.
  - Brief, Oregon State Agricultural College to the Oregon State Board of Higher Curricula, May 18, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Outline of a Suggested Division of Work Between University of Oregon and Oregon State Agricultural College, June 5, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Report to the Board of Higher Curricula, April 27, 1928 (Box 1)
  - "Statement of Oregon State Agricultural College to the State Board of Higher Curricula", May 2, 1928 (Box 1)
  - "Statements by Representatives of Oregon State College Before Curricula Committee of State Board of Higher Education", December 8, 1941 (Box 1)
- Resolutions Adopted by State Board of Higher Education, 1935; Series V (Reel 82)
  This series is comprised of a document entitled "Resolutions Adopted July 22, 1935, by the State Board of Higher Education Regarding Dr. Kerr, Retiring Chancellor."
- Biography of William Jasper Kerr, Series VI (Reel 82)
  This series is comprised of an excerpt from Edwin T. Reed's William Jasper Kerr, A Biography.
- Publications, 1908-1964; Series VII
  Series VII contains publications authored by William J. Kerr and members of Oregon Agricultural College between 1908 and 1964. Topics include the importance of Home Economics during wartime, the construction of the Memorial Union, higher education in Oregon, and the state of land grant institutions. The series also contains programs and materials from the dedication of the Kerr Library.
  - OSC - Illustrated Booklets, 1929-1930 (Reel-folder 82.1)
  - Relations of Land-Grant Colleges to State University, 1908 (Reel-folder 82.2)
  - OAC - Sources of Income and Departments of Instruction, 1908 (Reel-folder 82.3)
  - National Education Association - Session at Harvard, 1910 (Reel-folder 82.4)
  - Some Land Grant College Problems, 1910 (Reel-folder 82.5)
  - Education and the World War, 1917 (Reel-folder 82.6)
  - The Spirit of the Land Grant Institution, 1931 (Reel-folder 82.7)
    Also in Box 1
  - Recent Experiences - Centralized Control of Higher Education in Oregon, 1933 (Reel-folder 82.8)
  - Phi Kappa Phi Journal, 1934 (Reel-folder 82.9)
  - Oregon Problems in Marketing Agriculture and Industrial Products, 1938 (Reel-folder 82.10)
  - William Jasper Kerr - dedication of Library address, 1964 (Reel-folder 82.11)
  - Letter to State Board of Higher Education, 1931 (Reel-folder 82.12)
  - Administrative Regulations, 1921 (Box 1)
- OSC - U of O Controversy, 1937; Series VIII (Reel 82)
  Series VIII is comprised of a memo drafted by Godfrey Vernon Cospon regarding the reorganization of Oregon Agricultural College and the University of Oregon and the ensuing controversy.
- Reports to the Board of Regents, 1909-1929; Series IX
  This series contains reports to the Board of Regents summarizing the state of Oregon Agricultural College between 1909 and 1914. The series also contains a report for 1929.
  - Reports, 1909-1914 (Reel 82)
  - Report, 1929 (Box 1)
- Reorganization, 1931-1932; Series X
  This series is comprised of materials relating to the reorganization of Oregon Agricultural College and the University of Oregon in 1931-1932. The contents of this series relate to the reassignment of subject specialities, programs, faculty, and funding between the two universities.
  - Agriculture (Reel-folder 82.1)
  - Architecture - Landscape (Reel-folder 82.2)
  - Art (Reel-folder 82.3)
  - Brief - Educational Survey (Reel-folder 82.4)
  - Budgetary Material (Reel-folder 82.5)
    Also found in Box 5
  - Budgetary Material (continued) (Reel-folder 83.5)
  - Building Projects - Self-financing (Reel-folder 83.6)
  - Commerce (Reel-folder 83.7)
  - Cost data (Reel-folder 83.8)
  - Curricula (Reel-folder 83.9a)
  - Curricula Committee (Reel-folder 83.9b)
  - Dormitories (Reel-folder 83.10a)
  - Director of Dormitories (Reel-folder 83.10b)
  - Education (Reel-folder 83.11)
  - Enrollment (Reel-folder 83.12)
  - Extension - Radio, Summer School, Research (Reel-folder 83.13)
  - Extra Compensation for Staff Members (Reel-folder 83.14)
  - Field of Higher Education Developed in Oregon (Reel-folder 83.15)
  - Graduate Work (Reel-folder 83.16)
  - High School Relations (Reel-folder 83.17)
  - Home Economics (Reel-folder 83.18)
  - Journalism and News Service (Reel-folder 83.19)
  - Library (Reel-folder 83.20)
  - Lower Division (Reel-folder 83.21)
  - Military (Reel-folder 83.22)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel-folder 83.23)
  - Mines (Reel-folder 83.24)
  - Music (Reel-folder 83.25)
  - Normal Schools (Reel-folder 83.26)
  - Personnel (Deans and Directors) and Location of School (Reel-folder 83.27)
  - Pharmacy (Reel-folder 83.28)
  - Physical Education (Reel-folder 83.29)
  - Press Bureau and Editor's Office (Reel-folder 83.30)
  - Public Speaking (Reel-folder 83.31)
  - Reports - General
    - Budgetary and Financial (Reel-folder 83.32a)
    - Attitudes of University People (Reel-folder 83.32b)
    - Executive Secretary's Prerogatives and Authority (Reel-folder 83.32c)
    - Methods of Procedure (Reel-folder 83.32d)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel-folder 83.32e)
  - Research (Reel-folder 83.33)
  - Rural Organization - College, University (Reel-folder 83.34)
  - Salary Analysis and Personnel (Reel-folder 83.35a)
  - Salary Cuts (Reel-folder 83.35b)
  - Science (Reel-folder 83.36)
  - Social Science (Reel-folder 83.37)
  - Student Welfare - Housing, Deferred Pledging (Reel-folder 83.38)
  - U of O (Reel-folder 83.39)
  - Brief, Oregon State Agricultural College to the Oregon State Board of Higher Education Regarding the Survey of Oregon State Institutions of Higher Learning, April 18, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Supplementary Brief, Oregon State Agricultural College to the State Board of Higher Education, In Reply to the Twelve Briefs of the University of Oregon Dated April 20, 1931, April 27, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Second Supplementary Brief, Oregon State Agricultural College to the State Board of Higher Education, In Reply to the Eleven Resolutions Proposed by the University of Oregon, May 1, 1931, May 13, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Joint Statement to the State Board of Higher Education Submitted by the Presidents of the State University and the State College, May 27, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Reply to Dean Faville's Brief on the Commerce School Problem from Oregon State Agricultural College to Oregon State Board of Higher Education, 27 May 1931 (Box 2)
  - Survey of Public Higher Education in Oregon, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Course Changes Proposed for 1931/32 Catalog (Box 2)
  - Survey Commission Records, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - Survey Commission Records, undated (Box 2)
  - "A Study of Facts and Figures Bearing on Music", 1932 (Box 2)
  - "Basic Data Showing Existing Conditions in the Science Departments of Oregon State College", 1932 (Box 2)
  - Science Departments, Oregon State College, Cost of Instruction per Course and by Departments, 1931-1932 (Box 5)
  - Report to the Oregon State Board of Higher Education Curricula Committee on Vocational Education and Teacher Training, February 1932 (Box 5)
- College Surveys, 1928-1930; Series XI
  This series is comprised of four bound volumes relating to surveys of land grant institutions conducted by the U.S. Bureau of Education. It includes one volume of completed portions of the survey for Oregon Agricultural College, one volume providing a detailed report of the state of higher education in Oregon, and two volumes of results of the survey from other institutions across the United States.
  - Oregon State College to U.S. Bureau of Education: Land-Grant College Survey., 1928 (Box 3)
  - Survey of Oregon State Institutions of Higher Learning as Made by the United State Office of Education, Department of the Interior., 1930 (Box 3)
  - Survey of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities, U.S. Department of the Interior Bulletin. Volume 1., 1930 (Box 4)
  - Survey of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities, U.S. Department of the Interior Bulletin. Volume 2., 1930 (Box 4)